Luan da Fonseca Santos

luanfs.github.io | luanfsantos14@gmail.com

Summary

I am currently a Postdoctoral Researcher at Princeton University working at the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Adminstration's Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory (NOAA-GFDL). I hold a PhD degree in Applied Mathematics from the University of São Paulo. My primary research area focuses on advancing numerical techniques for weather/climate models, specifically the dynamical core development.

EXPERIENCE

Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences Program, Princeton University

Princeton, NJ, USA

 $Postdoctoral\ Researcher$

July 2024 - Present

- Implementing and evaluating specific enhancements to FV3's numerical algorithms to advance the accuracy and efficiency of FV3-based weather and climate models. Supervisors: Dr. Lucas Harris and Dr. Joseph Mouallem.
- Working at the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Adminstration's Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory (NOAA-GFDL) with the FV3 team.

Institute of Mathematics and Statistics, University of São Paulo

São Paulo, SP, Brazil

Graduate Researcher Student

March 2018 - May 2024

- Developed topography-based locally refined grids for South America for the NCAR MPAS model. Implemented a moist shallow-water model to assess these grids, resulting in a paper published in an international peer-reviewed journal.
- Developed and implemented an enhanced transport scheme for the NOAA-GFDL FV3 model with minimal additional computational overhead, resulting in a paper submitted for revision.
- Participated in a two-week research visit to the Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences Program at Princeton University and the Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory (hosts: Dr. Joseph Mouallem and Dr. Lucas Harris), where I gave a talk to the FV3 team.

Teaching Assistant

2017 - 2021

University of São Paulo

São Paulo, SP, Brazil

- Grad courses:
 - $1^{\rm St}$ sem/2019, $1^{\rm St}$ sem/2020 and $1^{\rm St}$ sem/2021 MAP5729 Introduction to Numerical Analysis (Institute of Mathematics and Statistics).
- Undergrad courses:
 - $2^{\mbox{nd}}$ sem/2019 MAP2320 Numerical methods in differential equations II (Institute of Mathematics and Statistics).
 - 2nd sem/2018 MAP0214 Numerical Calculus with Applications to Physics (Institute of Astronomy, Geophysics and Atmospheric Sciences).
 - 1st sem/2017 MAC0427 Non-linear Programming (Institute of Mathematics and Statistics).

EDUCATION

Institute of Mathematics and Statistics, University of São Paulo

São Paulo, SP, Brazil

Ph.D. in Applied Mathematics

March 2020 - May 2024

• Thesis title: Analysis of finite-volume advection schemes on cubed-sphere grids and an accurate alternative for divergent winds. Supervisor: Dr. Pedro Peixoto.

Institute of Mathematics and Statistics, University of São Paulo

São Paulo, SP, Brazil

M. Sc. in Applied Mathematics

March 2018 - March 2020

• Dissertation title: Analysis of mimetic finite volume schemes on classical and moist shallow water models considering topography based local refinement in spherical Voronoi grids. Supervisor: Dr. Pedro Peixoto.

Institute of Mathematics and Statistics, University of São Paulo

São Paulo, SP, Brazil 2014 - 2017

B. Sc. in Applied Mathematics (GPA: 9.3/10)

- Project title: Local refinement and interpolation in spherical icosahedral grids. Supervisor: Dr. Pedro Peixoto.
- Honorable mention for outstanding performance in the Applied Mathematics B.Sc. program.

Publication List

- Luan F. Santos and Pedro S. Peixoto (2024). Analysis of finite-volume transport schemes on cubed-sphere grids and an accurate scheme for divergent winds, **In review**, Preprint: http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.4866660.
- Luan F. Santos and Pedro S. Peixoto (2021). Topography based local spherical Voronoi grid refinement on classical and moist shallow-water finite volume models, Geosci. Model Dev. Discuss., https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-14-6919-2021.

Referee Activities

• Meteorological Applications (2024).

Talks

- 2023: Enhancing accuracy of FV3 finite-volume operators at FV3 group meeting, GFDL/NOAA, Princeton, USA.
- 2021: Topography based local spherical Voronoi grid refinement on classical and moist shallow-water finite volume models at *PDEs on the sphere 2021*, Offenbach, Germany (online).
- 2019: Poster Presentation, Topography based local refinement in spherical Voronoi grids at *PDEs on the sphere 2019, Montréal, Québec, Canada.*

PARTICIPATION AT EVENTS

- 2021: Participation in the ESCAPE2/Fondazione Alessandro Volta Summer school program Towards exascale computing for numerical weather prediction, Lake Como School of Advanced Studies (online).
- 2019: Participation in the Winter School in Atmospheric Numerical Modeling at CPTEC (Center for Weather Forecasting and Climate Studies), Cachoeira Paulista, SP, Brazil.

Grants

- Doctoral degree scholarship São Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP), grant 20/10280-4, 2020-2024.
- Master's degree scholarship São Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP), grant 17/25191-4, 2018-2020.
- Undergraduate research funding São Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP), grant 17/11542-0, 2017.

LINKS

- Personal webpage: https://luanfs.github.io/
- Google scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=D-uXvM0AAAAJ&hl=en
- ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9084-6170

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming languages: Fortran, Python (NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, Cartopy), C, and Matlab.
- Experience with parallel programming using OpenMP and MPI.
- General software and tools: Linux environment, Bash scripts, Git, remote servers, SSH, Tmux, Vim, LATEX.

Additional Information

• Date of birth: August 7, 1993.

• Citizenship: Brazilian.

• Gender: Male.

• Marital status: Married.

• Languages: Portuguese (native) and English (advanced).